Guide to the Marian Cox Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marian Cox Papers
1882-1972
1907-1964
YCAL MSS 750
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.08
(11 boxes)
Cox, Marian, 1882-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marian Cox, 1963, and of Donald Somers, 1972.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Marian Cox (b. 1882)
Born Mabel Marian Metcalfe in St. Louis, Missouri, in 1882, Marian Cox was the author of several books of fiction, non-fiction, and essays, including Crowds and the Veiled Woman ( New York: Funk & Wagnalls, 1910). She was a regular contributor to The Forum and other magazines. Her autobiography, The Sphinx Wore an Orchid, was published in 1967 (New York: Vintage Press).
Marian Metcalfe married Dr. John Watson Cox at the age of 16. She lived with her husband at the Murray Hill Mansion on 5th Avenue in New York, and Stonecrest Domain in Ridgefield, Connecticut, until his death in 1928. In 1934 she auctioned off both homes and their furnishings. Marian Cox was remarried in 1943 to Captain James Fay Logan, whose duty in the Maritime Service led him to the North and South Atlantic, the Mediterranean and the Indian Ocean.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, scrapbooks, personal papers, printed material, and realia relating to the life and work of Marian Cox, spanning the years 1882 to 1972, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1907 and 1963. Papers include correspondence relating chiefly to social engagements, writings by Cox (drafts and printed versions), auction catalogs from Cox's homes in New York and Connecticut, and books inscribed to Cox by their authors. Scrapbooks contain biographical information on Cox as well as clippings of articles written by and about Cox. Photographs include portraits of Cox, her friends, and her homes. Objects include shoes and dresses worn by Cox.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Papers, 1907-1964. II. Scrapbooks and Photographs, 1910-1972. III. Objects, 1882-1920.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Women authors, American -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- United States -- 20th Century; Scrapbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Cox, Marian, 1882-
- Papers, 1907-1964; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arrangement reflects the order in which material was received by the library.
  - Correspondence, 1910-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Earliest unpublished writings of Marian Cox, typescripts in binder, circa 1907-1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The American Peril in Europe," by Marian Cox, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brief of "The Sphinx Wore an Orchid," typescript carbon, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Undying Dead," collection of short stories, typescript and typescript carbon, in binder with magazines containing published stories, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Copyrights and blanket assignments, 1909-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Two catalogues of Cox residence auctions, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - American Moderns, by Maxwell Geismar, inscribed to Marian Cox by the author, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - History of Ridgefield, Connecticut, George L. Rockwell, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Paradise Found, by C. Wicksteed Armstrong; inscribed to Marian Cox by the author, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Social Register of New York, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Scrapbooks and Photographs, 1910-1972; Series II; 1.12; (4 boxes)
  Organized under two headings: Scrapbooks and Photographs.
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook of biographical information about Marian Cox, with photographs, by Donald Somers, 1972 June (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Donald Somers, 1972.
    - Scrapbook #1 of newspaper clippings, 1910-1944 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Scrapbook #2 of newspaper clippings and memorabilia, 1910-1951 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Scrapbook (loose pages), 1913, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 23)
  - Photographs
    - Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1932 May 26 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 24)
    - Cox, Marian, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Kennerly, Mitchell, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - McCabe, Joseph, 1917 November (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Shaw, George Bernard, 1913 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Sinclair, May, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Wagstaff, Blanch Shoemaker, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Murray Hill Mansion, New York, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 25)
    - Stonecrest Domain, Ridgefield, Connecticut, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Objects, 1882-1920; Series III; 0.71; (3 boxes)
  - Jeweled Heels and Marian Cox's First Shoes, circa 1882, undated (Box 9)
  - Blue and gold sequined dress worn by Marian Cox, circa 1920 (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - Red sequined dress worn by Marian Cox, circa 1920 (Box 11 (Oversize))